<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="ticket-structure" step="1" title="Load Bundle">

  <step n="1" title="Load Bundle">

    <goal>
      Read the bundle into working memory. The Design Summary (written
      by ticket-design) is the primary input — its artifact-chain
      shape informs the ticket's structure.
    </goal>

    <substep n="1a" title="Locate the Bundle">
      <ask>
        Which ticket bundle should I structure?

        Paste the bundle directory path or the ticket file path. The
        bundle should already have both a Readiness Summary section
        (written by ticket-grill) AND a Design Summary section
        (written by ticket-design) in the ticket body.
      </ask>
      <action>
        Validate the path. Store bundle paths in session (incl.
        {{session.worklog_path}}). Verify the WORKLOG contains BOTH
        "## Q↔R Readiness Summary" AND "## Design Summary". If either is
        absent, halt — the user must run the prior phase first (ticket-grill
        or ticket-design).
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="1b" title="Read Bundle Files">
      <action>
        Read the ticket, research, and questions files completely.
        Extract:
        - Primary tag and slug
        - Design Summary content (artifact chain, decision points,
          risk areas, locked DRs)
        - Any prior structure attempts (a session resuming
          ticket-structure may have a partial outline already present)
        - Linked DRs (their decisions may shape sections — e.g., a
          DR about a multi-tenancy choice means the structure outline
          should have a "Data Isolation" section even if the recipe
          doesn't mandate it)

        Store in session: primary_tag, slug, design_summary,
        artifact_chain, locked_drs, prior_structure_attempt.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="1c" title="Display Load Summary">
      <output>
        Structure-phase bundle loaded:
        - Slug: {{slug}}
        - Primary tag: {{primary_tag}}
        - Design Summary: present ({{design_summary_line_count}} lines)
        - Artifact chain length: {{count}} items
        - Linked DRs: {{count}}
        - Prior structure attempt: {{yes / no}}

        Proceeding to shape selection.
      </output>
    </substep>

  </step>

  <guidance>

    <section title="What the Design Summary tells us about structure">
      <description>
        The Design Summary's artifact chain hints at section grouping.
        For a feature ticket with chain [DR → Brief update → ADR →
        Architecture → Spec → Implementation], the ticket's structure
        will likely include sections for the product decision (linking
        the DR), the architectural decision (linking the ADR), the
        behavioral contract (referenced from the future Spec), and the
        implementation scope. Each chain item maps loosely to one or
        more sections; the recipe formalizes the mapping per tag.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="DR-driven section additions">
      <description>
        Each linked DR is a load-bearing decision. The structure should
        SURFACE these decisions in dedicated sections (or sub-sections),
        not bury them in prose. Examples:
        - DR on multi-tenancy → "Data Isolation Strategy" section
        - DR on vendor choice → "Vendor Selection" section
        - DR on scope boundary → "What This Does NOT Cover" section

        These additions may override recipe defaults; step 2 reconciles.
      </description>
    </section>

  </guidance>

</step-file>
