<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="ticket-structure" step="3" title="Draft and Align" critical="true">

  <step n="3" title="Draft and Align" critical="true">

    <goal>
      Present the Structure Outline draft to the user for confirmation
      or adjustment. Loop on adjustments until the outline is locked.
      Firm checkpoint per spec §3.3.
    </goal>

    <substep n="3a" title="Present Outline">
      <ask>
        Present the user with:

        Structure outline proposal:

        {{structure_outline_draft}}

        Does this structure work for the ticket?

        Options:
        - Confirm (Recommended if it looks right): lock the outline and proceed to ticket-plan
        - Add a section: I'll insert a section you propose
        - Remove a section: drop a recipe section we don't need
        - Reorder: change the section sequence
        - Add/remove Parts: toggle the Part-grouping decision
        - Reshape entirely: scrap the draft and propose a custom outline from scratch
        - Loop back to ticket-design: this exposes a design gap that needs revisiting
      </ask>
    </substep>

    <substep n="3b" title="Handle User Response">
      <check if="user confirms">
        <action>
          Lock {{structure_outline_draft}} as
          {{structure_outline_final}}. Proceed to step 4.
        </action>
      </check>

      <check if="user adjusts (add/remove/reorder/parts-toggle)">
        <action>
          Apply the adjustment to the draft. Re-loop to substep 3a to
          re-present. Cap on iterations: 5; if the outline isn't
          locking after 5 rounds, surface this and ask the user
          whether to switch to fully-custom mode or loop back to
          ticket-design.
        </action>
        <goto step="3"/>
      </check>

      <check if="user requests full reshape">
        <action>
          Discard {{structure_outline_draft}}. Re-enter step 2 with
          shape_mode = "fully-custom" forced. Draft a fresh outline.
          Then re-loop to substep 3a.
        </action>
        <goto step="2"/>
      </check>

      <check if="user loops back to ticket-design">
        <action>
          Append a note to the questions file:
          "Structure phase loop-back: design gap surfaced — {{specifics}}.
          User invoked ticket-design re-entry from ticket-structure step 3."

          Stamp last_updated on the questions file. Exit this skill
          cleanly. User invokes ticket-design via menu (TD); that skill
          will see the new note and re-align.

          NOTE: Looping back to ticket-design does NOT increment
          ticket-design's strike counter, because the loop-back is
          STRUCTURE-DRIVEN, not a foundational reversal. The strike
          counter only triggers on reversals of LOCKED foundational
          decisions, not on adjustments surfaced during structuring.
        </action>
      </check>
    </substep>

    <substep n="3c" title="Display Alignment Status">
      <output>
        Structure alignment:
        - Iterations: {{iteration_count}}
        - Final shape: {{shape_mode}}
        - Final section count: {{count}}
        - Outcome: {{locked / looped-back / pending}}

        {{if locked: "Proceeding to finalize and handoff."}}
        {{if looped-back: "Skill exiting; ticket-design will handle re-alignment."}}
      </output>
    </substep>

  </step>

  <guidance>

    <section title="Iteration cap is a soft warning, not a hard limit">
      <description>
        5 iterations on the outline suggests the agent is missing a
        load-bearing concern (each adjustment is revealing a new gap).
        At 5 rounds, surface the pattern to the user and recommend
        either fully-custom mode or loop-back to ticket-design.
        Continuing past 5 without escalation produces a structure that
        keeps shifting; eventually the user will accept something that
        doesn't actually fit.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Loop-back vs strike counter">
      <description>
        Looping back to ticket-design from this skill is NORMAL when a
        structure attempt reveals a design gap. It does NOT count as
        a foundational reversal because the user is not reversing a
        previously-locked decision — they are surfacing a need that
        wasn't visible in the Design Summary. ticket-design step 4
        classifies as 'redirect_scope_ungrilled' if appropriate, which
        does not increment strikes.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Reshape is more expensive than adjust">
      <description>
        Full reshape (scrap and restart) is costly — it discards work.
        Use only when the agent realizes the recipe was the wrong
        framework for this ticket. Most cases of "this doesn't feel
        right" are better served by add/remove/reorder iterations on
        the current draft.
      </description>
    </section>

  </guidance>

</step-file>
