<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="ticket-write" step="3" title="Write Sections (Iterate)">

  <step n="3" title="Write Sections (Iterate)" for-each="section in writing_plan.writing_order">

    <goal>
      Walk through every section in writing_order. For each: draft the
      section per its scope note, the Design Summary, and AGENT-BRIEF
      principles. Apply the section-quality checklist. Pause at planned
      checkpoints for user review.
    </goal>

    <substep n="3a" title="Draft This Section">
      <action>
        Identify the current section: {{current_section}}.
        Pull its scope note from the Structure Outline.
        Pull any findings for this section from {{section_findings}}.

        Draft the section body. Apply discipline from
        references/agent-brief-principles.md:
        - Durability over precision (no file paths in section body
          unless this is Risk Areas where evidence cites are bound)
        - Behavioral, not procedural (WHAT, not HOW)
        - Complete acceptance criteria where applicable (every AC
          independently testable)
        - Explicit scope boundaries where applicable
        - Reference linked DRs as wiki-links when the section content
          relates to a DR's decision
        - Cross-reference prior bundle artifacts (research file findings,
          Q&A entries) when content draws from them

        Section structure:
        - Level-2 heading: "## {{current_section.name}}"
        - Body content per AGENT-BRIEF principles
        - If section has subsections (per scope note), use level-3
          headings

        Length target: aim for the estimate from the Writing Plan,
        but treat it as a target not a hard limit. 50% under or 50%
        over surfaces a quality concern (ticket-verify will catch).
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="3b" title="Apply Section-Quality Checklist">
      <action>
        Run the section-quality checklist from
        agent-brief-principles.md against the drafted content:

        - [ ] Content within the section's stated scope?
        - [ ] Durable identifiers, not file paths (Risk exception aside)?
        - [ ] Behavior, not implementation?
        - [ ] Testable claims actually testable as written?
        - [ ] Wiki-links work (DR aliases resolve)?
        - [ ] Consistent with Design Summary's promises?

        If any answer is NO, re-draft this section before moving on.
        Do NOT advance to substep 3c with a NO outstanding.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="3c" title="Write Section to Ticket Body">
      <action>
        Append the drafted section to the ticket file body using the
        Edit tool. The section appends AFTER all prior content (which
        includes prior-phase summaries and any sections already
        written in this iteration).

        If the Writing Plan uses Parts, the first section of each Part
        is preceded by a "# Part N: {{part_title}}" level-1 heading
        before its level-2 section heading.

        After writing, log to session: {{written_sections}}.append(current_section).
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="3d" title="Checkpoint Pause">
      <check if="current_section ends a checkpoint per writing_plan.review_checkpoints">
        <action>
          Stamp last_updated on the ticket file. Use:
          uv run {base_dir}/scripts/stamp-frontmatter.py --file "{{ticket_path}}" --note "ticket-write checkpoint after section {{current_section.name}}; {{count}} of {{total}} sections complete."
        </action>
        <ask>
          Checkpoint reached after section "{{current_section.name}}"
          ({{count}} of {{total}} sections written, {{actual_lines_so_far}}
          of {{total_estimate}} lines estimated total).

          Review the section(s) written since the last checkpoint:
          {{list of section names in this batch}}

          - Continue (Recommended): proceed to next section
          - Adjust: I need to revise something; describe what
          - Pause: stop here; bundle on disk is the handoff state; resume later
        </ask>
        <check if="user adjusts">
          <action>
            Capture the adjustment. Apply via Edit. Re-run the section
            quality checklist on the adjusted content. Continue with
            the next section once the user reconfirms.
          </action>
        </check>
        <check if="user pauses">
          <action>
            Exit step 3 cleanly. The bundle on disk reflects the
            sections written so far. Resumption: re-invoke ticket-write;
            its step 1 will re-load the bundle, and the for-each
            iterator should skip already-written sections (compare
            section names in the ticket body to the writing_order
            list).
          </action>
        </check>
      </check>
      <check if="no checkpoint after this section">
        <action>
          Proceed to next iteration of step 3 (next section in
          writing_order).
        </action>
      </check>
    </substep>

  </step>

  <guidance>

    <section title="Iteration is the engine of this step">
      <description>
        Step 3 is a for-each over the writing_order list from the
        Writing Plan. The workflow engine processes each iteration
        with substeps 3a-3d. Within a single invocation of step 3,
        all sections get drafted (modulo checkpoint pauses where the
        user may pause).
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Resumption after pause">
      <description>
        If the user pauses at a checkpoint, the skill exits. Re-invoking
        ticket-write loads the bundle and starts at step 1 again.
        Step 3's for-each iterator needs to skip sections that are
        already in the ticket body — implement this by comparing
        section names (from writing_order) to level-2 headings in
        the existing ticket body. Skip any section whose heading
        already exists; start from the first not-yet-written section.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Length-checkpoint discipline">
      <description>
        Per the Writing Plan, mandatory checkpoints fire at Part
        boundaries and before Acceptance Criteria. Optional checkpoints
        fire mid-Part for Parts >400 lines. The skill HONORS the plan
        — does not add or skip checkpoints unilaterally. If a
        checkpoint feels excessive at run-time, that's a verify
        finding for review, not a write-time decision.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="The Acceptance Criteria section is special">
      <description>
        AC is the contract. Per the Writing Plan, AC is checkpointed
        BEFORE it's drafted (so the user approves the foundation
        first) — meaning the checkpoint fires AFTER the section
        immediately preceding AC. Then AC is drafted; then another
        checkpoint fires after AC for explicit AC review. This is the
        single most heavily-reviewed section.
      </description>
    </section>

  </guidance>

</step-file>
