<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="ticket-plan" step="3" title="Align with User">

  <step n="3" title="Align with User">

    <goal>
      Present the Writing Plan to the user. Lighter checkpoint than
      D or S phases (P is tactical), but still get explicit
      confirmation before ticket-write begins.
    </goal>

    <substep n="3a" title="Present Plan">
      <ask>
        Writing plan proposal:

        {{plan_draft}}

        Approve to proceed to ticket-write?

        - Confirm (Recommended if it looks right): lock the plan and proceed
        - Adjust writing order: change section sequence
        - Adjust subagent plan: change which sections dispatch subagents
        - Adjust checkpoints: add, remove, or move review pauses
        - Adjust length estimates: change my expectations on section length
        - Loop back to ticket-structure: this exposes a structural issue
      </ask>
    </substep>

    <substep n="3b" title="Handle Response">
      <check if="user confirms">
        <action>
          Lock {{plan_draft}} as {{plan_final}}. Proceed to step 4.
        </action>
      </check>

      <check if="user adjusts">
        <action>
          Apply the adjustment. Re-loop to substep 3a. Iteration cap
          of 3 (P is tactical; deeper churn signals a structural
          issue better solved by loop-back).
        </action>
        <goto step="3"/>
      </check>

      <check if="user loops back to ticket-structure">
        <action>
          Note in questions file: "Plan-phase loop-back: structural
          issue surfaced — {{specifics}}." Stamp last_updated. Exit
          cleanly. User invokes ticket-structure via menu (TS).

          As with ticket-structure→ticket-design loop-back, this does
          NOT increment ticket-design's strike counter — tactical
          loop-back is not a foundational reversal.
        </action>
      </check>
    </substep>

  </step>

  <guidance>

    <section title="P is tactical, not foundational">
      <description>
        Adjustments at this phase are normal and cheap. The plan can
        change without invalidating the Design Summary or the
        Structure Outline. Strike counter does not apply here — even
        big reorderings are still tactical.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="When to loop back vs adjust">
      <rules>
        <rule>Adjust: the section list is right, but the order or dispatch plan is off</rule>
        <rule>Adjust: a length estimate is wildly wrong</rule>
        <rule>Loop back to ticket-structure: a section in the outline doesn't actually need to exist (or one's missing)</rule>
        <rule>Loop back to ticket-design: a section's existence reveals a design gap (rare; usually surfaces in ticket-structure)</rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

  </guidance>

</step-file>
