<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="code-design" step="2" title="Present Current State">

  <step n="2" title="Present Current State">

    <substep n="2a" title="Draft Current State Section">
      <action>
        From research file findings, draft the Current state section:
        - Map the touched-area module/types/seams
        - Cite specific file:line references
        - Name patterns and invariants that exist
        - Stay focused: only the touched area, not the whole codebase

        Apply the tag-specific guidance already in the skeleton (the
        skeleton's "_Guidance ({{primary_tag}})_" line is the
        scaffold; you fill the content).
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="2b" title="Write to Design File">
      <action>
        Edit {{design_path}} — replace the "_(populated by code-design
        through brain-surgery conversation)_" placeholder under
        "## Current state" with the drafted content. Preserve the
        guidance line as a comment or remove it (your call — the
        section's purpose is now captured in the content itself).
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="2c" title="Present and Stress-Test">
      <ask>
        Current state drafted (see {{design_path}} → "## Current
        state" section).

        Summary: {{one-paragraph summary of the section}}

        Critical points to stress-test:
        - {{point 1}}
        - {{point 2}}
        - {{point 3}}

        Your response:
        - Accept (Recommended): proceed to Desired end state
        - Push back on a specific point: name the point + your concern
        - Reframe: the current-state framing is wrong; redirect
      </ask>
      <check if="user accepts">
        <action>Lock the section. Proceed to step 3.</action>
      </check>
      <check if="user pushes back">
        <action>
          Revise the section. Re-draft. Re-present. Loop within this
          step until alignment.
        </action>
      </check>
      <check if="user reframes">
        <action>
          This is a foundational reversal. Increment {{strike_count}}.
          See substep 2d.
        </action>
      </check>
    </substep>

    <substep n="2d" title="Foundational Reversal Strike Check">
      <check if="strike_count == 1">
        <action>
          Acknowledge the reframe. Note the invalidated work
          (research turns that no longer apply, design draft now
          stale). Re-draft current state per the new framing. Proceed.
        </action>
      </check>
      <check if="strike_count == 2">
        <ask>
          Second foundational reversal in this D-phase. The accumulated
          design draft is becoming inconsistent.

          Continue absorbing, or pause to consolidate?
          - Continue (Recommended for small reframes): I'll revise and proceed
          - Pause and consolidate: stop here; review what we have on disk; restart D-phase with the new framing
        </ask>
      </check>
      <check if="strike_count == 3">
        <ask>
          Third foundational reversal. The original D-phase scoping is
          increasingly clearly wrong.

          Recommendation: abort current D-phase. Archive the current
          bundle as research evidence. Restart D-phase with the new
          understanding.

          - Abort + restart (Recommended)
          - Continue anyway: I'll revise and proceed (the bundle's
            coherence is your responsibility from here)
        </ask>
        <check if="user picks abort">
          <action>
            Halt the skill. The bundle on disk is preserved as
            evidence. The codesmith primary agent surfaces the abort
            to the user with a restart recommendation.
          </action>
        </check>
      </check>
    </substep>

  </step>

</step-file>
