<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="ticket-prototype" step="5" title="Extract Findings and Return">

  <step n="5" title="Extract Findings and Return">

    <goal>
      Synthesize observations from the run into a structured findings block
      that the caller (ticket-grill) can append to the bundle's research
      file. Return the block + the preserved prototype path. Do NOT write
      a separate findings document.
    </goal>

    <substep n="5a" title="Synthesize Findings Block">
      <action>
        Compose a markdown block matching the research-finding shape. Format:

        ```md
        ### Prototype: {{session.prototype_name}} ({{ISO 8601 datetime}})

        **Question answered**: {{session.caller_question}}

        **Branch**: {{session.branch}}

        **What was built**: {{one-sentence description of the prototype}}

        **How it ran**: `{{session.run_command}}` (LOGIC) | "viewed in browser" (UI)

        **Findings**:
        {{numbered factual list of what was observed. Each finding is one
        or two sentences with no opinions or recommendations. Examples:

        1. SQLAlchemy SAVEPOINT-based nested transactions DO work on
           Postgres; both outer and inner tx report in_transaction()=True.
        2. Rolling back the inner transaction (savepoint) does NOT roll
           back the outer; the outer commits successfully.
        3. Sequelize-style nested-tx semantics are achievable; no fragile
           workarounds needed.}}

        **Preserved at**: `{{session.prototype_path}}` (refer to this path
        if the prototype needs to be re-run or inspected in the future)

        **Iterations**: {{session.iteration_count + 1}}
        ```

        Store as {{session.findings_block}}.

        Findings discipline:
        - FACTUAL — what was observed, not what should be done
        - SPECIFIC — cite the run output, the visible state, the user's UI report
        - SHORT — 3-7 findings max; if more, the question was too broad
        - NO RECOMMENDATIONS — those belong to ticket-design, not here
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="5b" title="Update Prototype README with Final Status">
      <action>
        Edit {{session.prototype_path}}/README.md to add a final section:

        ## Findings (captured)

        Findings recorded in: {{session.bundle_dir}}/research-*-{{session.slug}}.md
        on {{ISO 8601 datetime}}.

        See that file for the full finding block. This prototype is now
        evidence — preserved but not actively maintained.

        Iterations: {{session.iteration_count + 1}}
        Status: {{answered | partially_answered}}

        Use the Edit tool.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="5c" title="Return to Caller">
      <action>
        Compose the return payload:

        {
          status: "answered" | "partially_answered" | "aborted" | "escalate_to_spike",
          findings_block: {{session.findings_block}} (or null if aborted),
          prototype_path: {{session.prototype_path}},
          prototype_name: {{session.prototype_name}},
          branch: {{session.branch}},
          iteration_count: {{session.iteration_count + 1}},
          notes: {{any caveats or follow-ups for the caller}}
        }

        Return this payload as the skill's final output. The caller
        (ticket-grill in step-05) is responsible for:
        - Appending findings_block to the bundle's research file
        - Logging the prototype invocation in the questions file
        - Stamping last_updated on the research file

        ticket-prototype does NOT write to the research or questions
        files directly — that responsibility stays with the caller to
        keep the bundle's update path coherent in one place.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="5d" title="Present Final Output">
      <template-output section="Prototype Complete" critical="true">
        Prototype session complete.

        - Name: {{session.prototype_name}}
        - Branch: {{session.branch}}
        - Status: {{status}}
        - Iterations: {{iteration_count}}
        - Preserved at: {{session.prototype_path}}

        **Findings block** (returned to caller for inclusion in research file):

        {{session.findings_block}}

        Caller (ticket-grill) will append this to the bundle's research
        file in its own step-05.
      </template-output>
    </substep>

  </step>

  <guidance>

    <section title="The findings absorption pattern" critical="true">
      <description>
        Per QRDSPIV: "the answer extracted from a prototype belongs in the
        parent artifact". For ticketsmith, the "parent artifact" is the
        bundle's research file (kind: research). Prototype findings absorb
        into research findings; the prototype itself is preserved as a
        reference path linked from the finding.

        There is NO separate prototype-findings document. This was a
        possible reading of spec §4.1's "Prototype doc(s)" listing, but
        Lock 38 supersedes that: findings absorb, prototypes preserve.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Why ticket-prototype doesn't write the research file directly">
      <description>
        The bundle's update path is owned by ticket-grill's step-05
        (update-bundle-files). Centralizing all bundle writes in one
        place keeps the audit trail coherent — every bundle edit comes
        from one skill's responsibility. If ticket-prototype wrote
        directly to the research file, there would be two places that
        touch it, and bundle updates would diverge.

        Return the findings_block; let the caller decide where and when
        to write it. This also lets the caller (or future grill-adopting
        agents) include the findings under their own appropriate research
        section structure.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="When prototype findings are negative">
      <description>
        "X does not work" is a valid finding. "X works only under condition
        Y" is a valid finding. "The prototype crashed in a way that
        revealed underlying constraint Z" is a valid finding. Negative
        evidence saves implementation time downstream.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Aborted prototype handling">
      <rules>
        <rule>Aborted prototypes still preserve the prototype_path so the caller can record what was attempted</rule>
        <rule>The findings_block is null on abort, but the caller logs the attempt in the questions file</rule>
        <rule>An aborted prototype is not a failure of the skill — it is information ("this question is not prototype-able")</rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

  </guidance>

</step-file>
