<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="ticket-prototype" step="3" title="Scaffold Throwaway Files">

  <step n="3" title="Scaffold Throwaway Files">

    <goal>
      Create the minimal runnable that will answer the question. Single
      file when possible; surface state aggressively; one command to run.
      No build step if avoidable. No polish.
    </goal>

    <substep n="3a" title="Branch on Type">
      <check if="session.branch == 'logic'">
        <action>Proceed to substep 3b for LOGIC scaffolding.</action>
      </check>
      <check if="session.branch == 'ui'">
        <action>Proceed to substep 3c for UI scaffolding.</action>
      </check>
    </substep>

    <substep n="3b" title="Scaffold LOGIC Prototype">
      <action>
        Create a single runnable file in {{session.prototype_path}}/. The
        filename matches the prototype name plus a language-appropriate
        extension:

        - Python: prototype.py with PEP 723 inline metadata header for deps
        - TypeScript: prototype.ts (runnable via bun) or .js
        - Rust: main.rs (in a minimal Cargo project — exception to single-file rule)
        - Go: main.go
        - Shell: prototype.sh

        Write the code to answer {{session.caller_question}}. Conventions:
        - LOG / print intermediate state generously — the more state visible, the easier to interpret findings
        - Include the question as a header comment so future readers know what was being tested
        - Include the one-command invocation as a comment near the top
        - No CLI parsing, no error handling beyond what's necessary, no abstractions

        Example LOGIC prototype (Python with PEP 723):

        ```python
        # /// script
        # requires-python = ">=3.11"
        # dependencies = ["sqlalchemy>=2.0", "psycopg[binary]"]
        # ///
        """Question: Does SQLAlchemy support nested transactions on Postgres?
        Run: uv run prototype.py
        """
        from sqlalchemy import create_engine, text

        engine = create_engine("postgresql+psycopg://...")
        with engine.begin() as outer:
            print("OUTER tx state:", outer.in_transaction())
            with outer.begin_nested() as inner:
                print("INNER tx state:", inner.in_transaction())
                inner.execute(text("INSERT ..."))
                # Probe state, check savepoints, etc.
        print("DONE")
        ```

        Write the file using the Write tool. Path: {{session.prototype_path}}/prototype.{{ext}}
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="3c" title="Scaffold UI Prototype">
      <action>
        Create 1-3 HTML files in {{session.prototype_path}}/. Conventions:

        - For single-variant questions: index.html
        - For multi-variant comparisons (per QRDSPIV note): variant-a.html,
          variant-b.html, variant-c.html with an index.html that links to all

        Each HTML file:
        - Self-contained (CSS and JS inline OR via a single CDN script if
          using a framework)
        - Uses the detected design system from step 2 if any
        - Includes the question as an HTML comment at the top
        - Surfaces interaction state visibly (e.g., display the current
          selection, highlight focused elements, show keyboard hints)
        - Loads with no build step — open in a browser, done

        For design-system-aware prototypes:
        - shadcn/ui via CDN: use the official CDN bundle OR write Tailwind
          utility classes directly (Tailwind via CDN script tag is fine)
        - Material UI / antd / Chakra: load via CDN scripts; use their
          component class names
        - Internal design system: reference its CSS file via relative or
          absolute path; use its component class names

        Write each file using the Write tool. List all created paths in
        {{session.scaffolded_files}}.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="3d" title="Write a README in the Prototype Directory">
      <action>
        Create {{session.prototype_path}}/README.md with:

        ```md
        # Prototype: {{session.prototype_name}}

        **Question**: {{session.caller_question}}
        **Branch**: {{session.branch}}
        **Created**: {{ISO 8601 datetime}}
        **For ticket**: {{session.slug}}

        ## How to run

        {{one-command instruction: e.g., "uv run prototype.py" or "open index.html in a browser"}}

        ## What this tests

        {{one-paragraph explanation of what the prototype is exercising and what observation answers the question}}

        ## Status

        Throwaway. Findings absorbed into {{session.bundle_dir}}/research-*.md.
        This directory may be archived or deleted once findings are recorded.
        ```

        Write using the Write tool.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="3e" title="Display Scaffold Summary">
      <output>
        Prototype scaffolded:
        - Path: {{session.prototype_path}}/
        - Files created: {{session.scaffolded_files}}
        - README: {{session.prototype_path}}/README.md

        Proceeding to run and observe.
      </output>
    </substep>

  </step>

  <guidance>

    <section title="Single-file discipline" critical="true">
      <description>
        LOGIC prototypes should be ONE file in 90% of cases. Multi-file
        scaffolding (separate modules, separate test file, separate config)
        is over-engineering for a throwaway. Exception: Rust requires a
        Cargo project structure; that's tolerated because the language
        forces it.

        UI prototypes may need 2-4 files (HTML + optional separate CSS or
        JS files, or per-variant HTML files). Beyond that, the question
        is probably too broad — split into multiple narrow prototypes.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="State surfacing">
      <description>
        The point of a prototype is to OBSERVE state. The agent's findings
        in step 5 come from what was visible during the run. Prototypes
        that hide state (silent successes, swallowed exceptions, internal
        booleans never logged) produce thin findings.
      </description>
      <rules>
        <rule>LOGIC: print() or console.log() at every interesting state transition</rule>
        <rule>LOGIC: print() exceptions with full tracebacks; do not swallow</rule>
        <rule>UI: render state visibly — current values, focus, hover, active variants</rule>
        <rule>UI: include a viewport indicator (e.g., a small label showing window width) for layout-dependent questions</rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

    <section title="No polish, no production quality">
      <rules>
        <rule>No CLI argument parsing unless the prototype genuinely needs parameters</rule>
        <rule>No tests for the prototype itself</rule>
        <rule>No logging configuration; print() is fine</rule>
        <rule>No type annotations beyond what runs without errors</rule>
        <rule>No README sections beyond what's in substep 3d</rule>
        <rule>If the prototype works on the first run and answers the question, do not iterate to "improve" it</rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

  </guidance>

</step-file>
