<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="ticket-prototype" step="1" title="Receive Question and Choose Branch">

  <step n="1" title="Receive Question and Choose Branch">

    <goal>
      Receive the question from the caller, decide whether a LOGIC or UI
      prototype fits, and confirm with the user if the choice is ambiguous.
      The branch decision shapes everything in steps 2-5.
    </goal>

    <substep n="1a" title="Read Caller Context">
      <action>
        The caller (ticket-grill or another grill-adopting skill) invoked
        this skill with context. Extract:

        - The question being investigated (one sentence, from the turn focus)
        - The bundle directory path
        - The slug
        - Any prior findings already in the bundle's research file relevant to this prototype
        - The user's stated language/framework preferences if any

        Store in session as {{session.caller_question}},
        {{session.bundle_dir}}, {{session.slug}}, etc.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="1b" title="Apply Branch Heuristics">
      <action>
        Decide LOGIC vs UI:

        **LOGIC branch fits when**:
        - The question concerns state transitions ("does X happen when Y?")
        - The question concerns data shape or computation ("what does the
          output look like when input is Z?")
        - The question concerns timing or concurrency ("does this race
          condition surface in practice?")
        - The question concerns integration ("does library X actually
          support method Y?")
        - The answer can be expressed in terminal output, JSON, or a
          structured log

        **UI branch fits when**:
        - The question concerns layout or visual hierarchy
        - The question concerns interaction flow (clicks, navigation, transitions)
        - The question concerns information density or accessibility
        - The question concerns multiple visual variants the user wants to compare
        - The answer requires the user to LOOK at something to evaluate it

        If both could apply, default to LOGIC — it is faster and produces
        more concrete evidence.

        Store {{session.branch}}: "logic" or "ui".
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="1c" title="Choose Prototype Name">
      <action>
        Slug the prototype with a short kebab-case name derived from the
        question:
        - 2-4 words
        - Names what is being tested, not the test method
        - Avoid generic names like "test" or "experiment"

        Examples:
        - "Does Sequelize support nested transactions on Postgres?" -> sequelize-nested-tx
        - "What does a horizontal task list look like with 50 items?" -> horizontal-tasks-density
        - "Can we extract team_id from the JWT in middleware without a re-query?" -> jwt-team-extract

        Store as {{session.prototype_name}}.

        Validate: {{session.bundle_dir}}/prototypes/{{session.prototype_name}}/
        does not already exist. If it does, append -2 / -3 until unique.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="1d" title="Confirm Branch and Name">
      <ask>
        Prototype plan:
        - Branch: {{session.branch}}
        - Name: {{session.prototype_name}}
        - Will be scaffolded at: {{session.bundle_dir}}/prototypes/{{session.prototype_name}}/

        Question being answered: {{session.caller_question}}

        Proceed?
        - Confirm (Recommended): proceed to scaffold
        - Switch branch: change LOGIC↔UI
        - Rename: change the prototype name
        - Cancel: abort prototyping; return null findings to the caller
      </ask>
      <check if="user cancels">
        <action>
          Halt the skill. Return {findings: null, prototype_path: null,
          cancelled: true} to the caller. ticket-grill will log the
          cancellation in its Q&A entry.
        </action>
      </check>
    </substep>

  </step>

  <guidance>

    <section title="When neither branch fits">
      <description>
        If a question genuinely cannot be answered by either branch (e.g.,
        "will users adopt this feature?"), prototyping is the wrong tool.
        Such questions require user research, A/B testing, or beta
        rollout — none of which fit a throwaway-prototype session.
        Recommend to the caller that this question be deferred to a
        post-launch validation activity, not absorbed into ticket-writing
        Q↔R.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Anti-patterns to refuse">
      <rules>
        <rule>Refuse to prototype a full feature. Prototypes answer ONE question at a time. If the user asks for "a prototype of the whole team workspaces flow", split into multiple narrow prototypes or escalate to a spike ticket</rule>
        <rule>Refuse to prototype code that should be production. If the question is "how would I implement X in production?", that is implementation work — not prototyping. Return findings: "use the actual implementation skill, not a throwaway prototype"</rule>
        <rule>Refuse multi-day prototypes. Throwaway means 30-90 minutes typically; an hour or two at the outside. Anything longer becomes a spike ticket (kind: exploration tag)</rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

    <section title="Branch examples">
      <example type="logic">
        Q: "Does the existing pagination middleware support cursor-based pagination?"
        Branch: LOGIC
        Why: Terminal-runnable; answer is yes/no with a code snippet showing how (or proving it can't).
      </example>
      <example type="logic">
        Q: "What does the JWT payload look like after the new claims are added?"
        Branch: LOGIC
        Why: Terminal output suffices. Print the payload; done.
      </example>
      <example type="ui">
        Q: "How does the team-switcher dropdown look with 50 teams vs 5 teams?"
        Branch: UI
        Why: Requires visual inspection. Two variants to compare.
      </example>
      <example type="ui">
        Q: "Is the task-detail modal readable on mobile or does it need a different layout?"
        Branch: UI
        Why: Requires visual + interactive inspection at multiple viewports.
      </example>
    </section>

  </guidance>

</step-file>
