<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="research-risk" step="4" title="Build Risk Register">

  <step n="4" title="Build Risk Register">

    <substep n="4a" title="Pre-Mortem Pass">
      <action>
        Before cataloguing, run a pre-mortem over the scan findings:
        assume this approach has failed in production six months from now
        — what were the causes? This surfaces failure modes the
        category scans may have under-weighted, especially at the seams
        between categories (a performance fix that opens a security hole;
        an operational shortcut that risks data integrity).
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="4b" title="Grade Each Risk">
      <action>
        For each risk identified, record:
        - Category: which lens it falls under
        - Risk: what could go wrong, stated concretely
        - Evidence: file:line, URL, or thoughts/ alias grounding the risk
        - Likelihood (High / Medium / Low): the evidence-grounded
          probability it materializes — justify with the evidence, not a
          hunch ("HIGH: input is user-controlled and reaches the query
          unescaped [cite]")
        - Impact (High / Medium / Low): severity if it does materialize
        - Mitigation: the standard countermeasure for this risk class,
          stated factually ("mitigated by parameterized queries") — NOT
          a remediation order for our code. Where our codebase already
          applies the mitigation elsewhere, cite it.

        Rank by likelihood × impact; High/High risks lead the register.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="4c" title="Compose the Register">
      <action>
        Compose the body per references/research/document-format
        body-skeleton. Fixed top: the approach assessed, and a Summary
        ranking the top risks (the High/High and High/Medium first).
        Variable middle: the risk register grouped by category, entries
        ordered by severity within each. Bottom: Open Questions
        (categories assessed from internal evidence only, scans deferred
        at the web gate).

        Adversarial honesty: if the approach is genuinely low-risk, say
        so — but surface the residual and low risks rather than declaring
        all-clear. A scan that found nothing worth noting is a scan that
        did not look hard enough.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="4d" title="Review the Register" optional="true">
      <check if="INTERACTIVE">
        <template-output section="Risk Register">
          Present the register for review before persistence.

          [a] Revise (re-scan a category, sharpen a likelihood grade)
          [c] Continue to persistence
          [y] YOLO
        </template-output>
      </check>
    </substep>

  </step>

</step-file>
