<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="ticket-design" step="3" title="Present and Align" critical="true">

  <step n="3" title="Present and Align" critical="true">

    <goal>
      Present the design proposal to the user as a brain-surgery
      conversation. Capture the user's response (confirm / redirect /
      reverse / abort) and pass it to step 4 for classification and
      strike-counter handling. This step is critical="true" — cannot
      be skipped, even in YOLO mode. Per QRDSPIV §D: "D is a
      conversation, not a document."
    </goal>

    <substep n="3a" title="Present the Proposal">
      <ask>
        Present the user with the full Design Summary draft. Format the
        ask as:

        Here's how I understand the work:

        {{session.design_summary_draft}}

        Brain-surgery question: does this look right?

        Options:
        - Confirm (Recommended if it looks right): the design is correct; lock and move to ticket-structure
        - Redirect scope: scope is wrong; describe what's off
        - Adjust the chain: scope is right but the artifact chain is wrong; describe the correction
        - Adjust risk: scope and chain are right but a risk is mis-stated; describe
        - Reverse a previous decision: I want to revisit something previously locked (DR or Q↔R outcome); name what
        - Abort: stop the workflow

        Capture the user's response verbatim where possible. Classify in
        step 4.

        Store as {{session.user_response}}: {classification_hint, verbatim,
        details}.
      </ask>
    </substep>

    <substep n="3b" title="Capture Verbatim">
      <action>
        Record the user's exact words in {{session.strike_log}} as a
        timestamped entry (whether or not this turns into a strike, the
        verbatim record helps step 4 classify correctly).

        Entry format:
        {
          timestamp: ISO 8601,
          ticket_design_iteration: N,
          user_response_classification_hint: "confirm" | "redirect" | "adjust_chain" | "adjust_risk" | "reverse" | "abort",
          verbatim: <user's text>,
          notes: <agent's initial assessment, refined in step 4>
        }
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="3c" title="Display Response Summary">
      <output>
        User response captured:
        - Classification hint: {{session.user_response.classification_hint}}
        - Length: {{verbatim_word_count}} words

        Proceeding to redirect/strike handling.
      </output>
    </substep>

  </step>

  <guidance>

    <section title="Why this is a single conversational ask">
      <description>
        D-phase is brain-surgery — one big presentation, one big
        response. The proposal is dense; the user needs to take it in
        as a whole and react. Breaking it into per-section asks
        ("does the artifact chain look right? does the risk look right?
        does the decision-points list look right?") fragments the
        alignment conversation and loses the "do these pieces work as
        a WHOLE" signal that brain-surgery alignment is meant to
        produce.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Recommended-first protocol">
      <rules>
        <rule>"Confirm" is always offered FIRST in the options list with "(Recommended)" when the draft looks defensible</rule>
        <rule>If the draft has known weaknesses (e.g., a risk area was speculatively included), surface that in the ask text: "I'm less sure about the second risk — wanted to flag for review"</rule>
        <rule>Do not present the design as a fait accompli; the user CAN redirect or reverse</rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

    <section title="The verbatim record matters">
      <description>
        Subtle word choice in the user's response shapes step 4's
        classification. "I'd like to revisit Option A vs Option B" is
        a REVERSE (it's questioning a locked alternative selection).
        "I think the artifact chain should also include a UX spec
        update" is an ADJUST_CHAIN (additive, not a reversal). The
        verbatim record preserves the signal for step 4 to read.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Critical step, no YOLO skip">
      <description>
        critical="true" on this step is per the workflow engine's
        critical-rules. YOLO mode auto-completes everything else, but
        D-phase alignment is the single point where the user gates the
        downstream phases — bypassing it produces ticket-structure on
        an unconfirmed design.
      </description>
    </section>

  </guidance>

</step-file>
