<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="ticket-design" step="2" title="Draft Design Proposal">

  <step n="2" title="Draft Design Proposal">

    <goal>
      Compose the brain-surgery proposal: the artifact chain this work
      requires, the decision points future user touchpoints will surface,
      and the risk areas where friction is most likely. Tag recipe drives
      depth.
    </goal>

    <substep n="2a" title="Load Tag Recipe (if available)">
      <action>
        Check whether a tag-recipe file exists at
        .vera/shared/references/tag-recipes/{{session.primary_tag}}.md
        (these are Phase 4 references; may not exist yet during
        ticketsmith development). If present, load it; it provides
        depth guidance for the primary tag.

        Tag-recipe contents (when authored) specify:
        - Depth expectation for D-phase per tag
        - Mandatory artifact-chain elements per tag
        - Typical risk profile per tag

        If absent, use built-in defaults based on the spec §8 tag
        descriptions: feature → full depth, bug → medium, exploration →
        learning-focused, hotfix → minimal, infrastructure → medium,
        chore → minimal.

        Store {{session.tag_recipe}} (or "default" if no file found).
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="2b" title="Identify the Artifact Chain">
      <action>
        Based on the Q↔R findings and the tag recipe, identify the
        downstream artifacts that will need creating or modifying to
        deliver this work. Categories:

        - **DRs** (`kind: decision`): hard-to-reverse decisions that will
          need recording. Some may already be linked from prior turns;
          new ones may surface during structure or implementation.
        - **Specs** (`kind: spec`, if the spec layer exists in the
          target harness): formal contracts for the behavior.
        - **Sub-tickets**: if Q↔R revealed multi-slice scope, the
          implementation-QRDSPIV will decompose. Surface that here.
        - **Live document updates**: brief, architecture, policy,
          manifest may need touching.
        - **Implementation**: the code that delivers the behavior.
        - **Tests / verification**: if not implicit in implementation.

        Per the worked example in QRDSPIV: a feature ticket's chain
        typically reads "DR → Brief update → ADR → Architecture update
        → Spec → Implementation."

        Order the chain by dependency. Store as {{session.artifact_chain}}.

        IMPORTANT: the artifact chain is SCOPING, not prescription. The
        agent is identifying what artifacts will be needed, not specifying
        their content. Per QRDSPIV §S: "Scope, don't prescribe."
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="2c" title="Identify Decision Points">
      <action>
        Walk through the artifact chain. For each artifact, identify
        whether the user will need to make a decision during its
        creation that goes beyond mechanical work:

        - ADR creation typically requires a user decision on the
          chosen alternative
        - Spec creation may surface edge-case decisions
        - Implementation may surface technology-version or library
          decisions

        List decision points as: "Step N (artifact X): user decides Y."

        Store as {{session.decision_points}}. This is the calendar of
        future user touchpoints that downstream implementation-QRDSPIV
        will need to honor.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="2d" title="Identify Risk Areas">
      <action>
        Synthesize from the research findings: where is the friction
        most likely to surface? Risk areas typically include:

        - Cross-cutting code touch (e.g., "auth middleware touches 47 test files")
        - Migration steps (data migration, schema change, API version bump)
        - Permissions or security implications
        - Performance-critical paths
        - Third-party dependency surfaces (vendor APIs, OS-level)
        - Breaking changes to public contracts

        Be specific. Cite the research findings that surface each risk
        (file paths, prior-art notes from the research file).

        Store as {{session.risk_areas}}: list of {area, evidence,
        impact-if-mismanaged}.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="2e" title="Draft the Design Summary Block">
      <action>
        Compose the Design Summary as it will appear in the ticket body.
        Format:

        ```md
        ## Design Summary

        ### The work

        {{2-3 sentences restating what is being built, drawing from the
        Q↔R Readiness Summary's scope statement and refining if D-phase
        surfaces clarifications}}

        ### Artifact chain

        {{numbered list of downstream artifacts in dependency order; one
        line each: "1. DR — record decision on X. 2. Brief update — add
        capability Y. 3. ..."}}

        ### Decision points

        {{bullet list of future user touchpoints: "- Step 3 (ADR): user
        decides between option A, B, C"}}

        ### Risk areas

        {{bullet list: each risk with evidence cite and impact}}

        ### Locked DRs (this session)

        {{list of DR aliases that constrain the design; references back
        to the Q↔R phase's findings}}
        ```

        Store as {{session.design_summary_draft}}. This is the DRAFT;
        step 3 presents it to the user, who may redirect.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="2f" title="Display Draft for Internal Review">
      <output>
        Design Summary draft prepared. Composition:
        - Artifact chain: {{count}} items
        - Decision points: {{count}}
        - Risk areas: {{count}}
        - Locked DRs referenced: {{count}}

        Proceeding to brain-surgery alignment with user.
      </output>
    </substep>

  </step>

  <guidance>

    <section title="Scoping, not prescribing" critical="true">
      <description>
        Per QRDSPIV §S: "At the ticket level, S stays high-level. The
        ticket creator does not need to know the internal structure of
        each artifact type. 'We need a spec covering teams, membership,
        and permissions' is correct scoping. 'The spec needs 6 Kipling
        categories with these specific criteria' is too deep — that's
        the spec creator's job during the spec's own S phase."

        Same principle applies to D at the ticket-writing layer. D-phase
        identifies WHAT artifacts and decisions are needed — not what
        the content of each artifact will be.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="No technical prescription">
      <rules>
        <rule>The Design Summary does NOT name implementation libraries unless they are constraints (e.g., "must use Sequelize because that's what the codebase uses"). Library selection during implementation is implementation-QRDSPIV's job</rule>
        <rule>The Design Summary does NOT specify file paths for new code</rule>
        <rule>The Design Summary does NOT prescribe vertical slices — that's the implementation-QRDSPIV's P-phase</rule>
        <rule>The Design Summary DOES cite specific files and modules from the research findings when surfacing risk (those are evidence, not prescription)</rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

    <section title="Risk-area evidence discipline">
      <description>
        Every risk area cites specific evidence from the research file.
        "Auth middleware refactor is risky" without evidence is hand-waving.
        "Auth middleware (src/middleware/auth.ts:42) is referenced by 38
        route handlers per the codebase-locator finding in research file
        Turn 4; refactoring will require updating each handler's
        req.user.id usage" is grounded.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="What if the artifact chain reveals decomposition">
      <description>
        Per spec §9, ticket-writing produces ONE ticket per session.
        Decomposition into sub-tickets is implementation-QRDSPIV's job
        (its P-phase). D-phase surfaces the LIKELY decomposition as a
        risk-area or in the artifact-chain narrative, but does NOT
        produce sub-tickets here.

        Example: "The implementation step is likely to decompose into
        3-4 vertical slices (model layer, middleware, route handlers,
        test migration) — this is downstream P-phase's job, not this
        ticket's scope."
      </description>
    </section>

  </guidance>

</step-file>
