<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="ticket-design" step="4" title="Handle Redirects and Strike Escalation">

  <step n="4" title="Handle Redirects and Strike Escalation">

    <goal>
      Classify the user's response and dispatch accordingly. The
      classification controls whether the skill confirms and proceeds,
      loops back to a prior phase, increments the strike counter, or
      recommends abort. Strike counter enforces Lock 31's three-strike
      escalation on foundational reversals.
    </goal>

    <substep n="4a" title="Classify the Response">
      <action>
        Refine {{session.user_response.classification_hint}} into a
        final classification:

        - **confirm**: user accepted the design; proceed to step 5
        - **redirect_scope_ungrilled**: user revealed a scoping concern
          NOT previously raised in Q↔R. Loop back to ticket-grill with
          the new focus.
        - **adjust_chain**: user modified the artifact chain (added or
          removed an artifact, reordered). NOT a foundational reversal —
          edit the draft and re-present.
        - **adjust_risk**: user modified a risk-area statement. NOT a
          foundational reversal — edit and re-present.
        - **foundational_reversal**: user reversed a previously LOCKED
          foundational decision. Examples:
          - Changing a confirmed scope ("actually, the work should NOT
            include the auth changes after all")
          - Reversing a DR's decision ("I want to reconsider the
            shared-tables vs RLS choice")
          - Rejecting a confirmed Q↔R outcome on a load-bearing question
          STRIKE COUNTER INCREMENTS.
        - **abort**: user explicitly wants to stop. Archive the bundle
          and exit.

        Use the verbatim record from substep 3b as the source of
        classification. When ambiguous, prefer the LESS severe
        classification (adjust over reverse; reverse over abort) but
        verify with one clarifying question.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="4b" title="Dispatch by Classification">
      <check if="classification == 'confirm'">
        <action>
          Lock {{session.design_summary_draft}} as
          {{session.design_summary_final}}. Proceed to step 5.
        </action>
      </check>

      <check if="classification == 'redirect_scope_ungrilled'">
        <action>
          Append a note to {{session.questions_path}} (Q&A entry) describing
          the new scoping concern. Stamp last_updated on the questions
          file via stamp-frontmatter.py.

          Present the user with:
          "This redirect surfaces a scoping gap not previously grilled.
          Recommend looping back to ticket-grill for an additional Q↔R
          turn focused on this gap. Confirm?"

          On confirm: exit this skill cleanly. The user invokes
          ticket-grill via the ticketsmith menu (TG). ticket-grill's
          step 1 will re-load the bundle and re-enter the loop at step 2.

          On decline (the user wants to proceed without grilling): treat
          as a force-skip; log in the questions file; loop back to step 2
          of THIS skill with the redirect absorbed (assume the user knows
          what they're doing).
        </action>
      </check>

      <check if="classification == 'adjust_chain' OR classification == 'adjust_risk'">
        <action>
          Edit the draft in {{session.design_summary_draft}} per the
          user's correction. Loop back to step 3 to re-present the
          adjusted version.
        </action>
        <goto step="3"/>
      </check>

      <check if="classification == 'foundational_reversal'">
        <action>
          Increment {{session.foundational_strikes}}.
          Append a strike entry to {{session.strike_log}}:
          {
            strike_n: {{session.foundational_strikes}},
            timestamp: ISO 8601,
            reversed_decision: <which DR / Q↔R outcome / scope element>,
            user_rationale: <verbatim>,
            agent_assessment: <one-line agent note>
          }

          Apply the strike-N protocol:
          - Strike 1 → substep 4c
          - Strike 2 → substep 4d
          - Strike 3 → substep 4e
        </action>
      </check>

      <check if="classification == 'abort'">
        <action>
          Proceed to substep 4f (archive and exit).
        </action>
      </check>
    </substep>

    <substep n="4c" title="Strike 1 Protocol">
      <action>
        Strike 1: ABSORB and LOOP BACK.

        Present to user:
        "Acknowledged — this is a reversal of a previously locked
        {{decision_type}}. I'll absorb the change. Identifying which
        Q↔R turns or research findings are invalidated:
        {{agent's list of invalidated bundle content}}

        Loop back recommendation: ticket-grill, to re-grill the
        affected scope. Alternatively: stay in this skill and
        re-draft the design with the new constraint."

        Append a strike-1 record to the questions file. Stamp
        last_updated.

        Ask user to confirm direction: loop to ticket-grill OR stay
        in ticket-design with the absorbed reversal.

        On loop: exit cleanly; user invokes ticket-grill via menu.
        On stay: loop back to step 2 of this skill with reversal
        absorbed.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="4d" title="Strike 2 Protocol">
      <action>
        Strike 2: SURFACE CONCERN.

        Present to user:
        "Second foundational reversal this session. The bundle is
        becoming inconsistent — prior turns are being invalidated.
        Recommend pausing to consolidate before continuing.

        Options:
        - Pause: review the bundle content; reconcile contradictions
          before next phase
        - Continue absorbing: proceed past this reversal (strike
          counter advances; one more reversal triggers abort
          recommendation)
        - Abort now: archive bundle as research evidence; start fresh
          Q↔R later"

        Append a strike-2 record to the questions file. Stamp
        last_updated.

        Ask user to confirm direction. On pause: exit cleanly with a
        pause note. On continue: loop back to step 2 with reversal
        absorbed. On abort: proceed to substep 4f.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="4e" title="Strike 3 Protocol">
      <action>
        Strike 3: RECOMMEND ABORT.

        Present to user:
        "Three foundational reversals this session. This pattern
        indicates the original Q↔R scoping was wrong — accumulated
        inconsistencies in the bundle now exceed what additional
        absorption can repair.

        Recommendation: ABORT this ticket-writing session. Archive the
        current bundle (status: abandoned, with a postscript explaining
        the abort) as research evidence. Start a fresh ticket-writing
        session with the new understanding from these reversals.

        Options:
        - Abort and archive (Recommended): mark the ticket
          status=abandoned; add a postscript; exit
        - Override and continue: I'll force one more attempt; strike
          counter logic ends; you accept the inconsistency risk
        - Pause: stop here without aborting; resume later with fresh
          context"

        Append a strike-3 record to the questions file. Stamp
        last_updated.

        Ask user to confirm. On abort: proceed to substep 4f. On
        override: loop back to step 2 with reversal absorbed; do NOT
        increment strike counter further. On pause: exit cleanly.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="4f" title="Abort Path">
      <action>
        Edit the ticket frontmatter: set status = abandoned. Append a
        postscript section to the ticket body:

        ## Session Abandoned

        - Reason: {{abort reason: explicit user abort OR three-strike escalation}}
        - Strikes accumulated: {{session.foundational_strikes}}
        - Strike log: see {{session.questions_path}} (entries timestamped this session)

        This bundle is preserved as research evidence. To start a fresh
        ticket-writing session on the same underlying request, invoke
        ticket-orient with a new slug and reference this bundle as prior
        art in the Orient Summary.

        Stamp last_updated on the ticket file with note: "Session
        abandoned per ticket-design step 4."

        Exit the skill cleanly. Bundle is preserved; status reflects the
        abandonment.
      </action>
    </substep>

  </step>

  <guidance>

    <section title="The classification call is the core skill craft" critical="true">
      <description>
        Most session-ending mistakes come from misclassifying a redirect
        as adjustment (under-counting strikes) or misclassifying an
        adjustment as reversal (over-counting strikes). When ambiguous,
        the agent asks ONE clarifying question before applying the
        strike protocol:

        "Just to be precise: are you reversing the previous decision on X
        (which would be a foundational change), or adjusting the
        artifact-chain to include something new (which is additive)?
        These trigger different protocols."

        The user's answer determines the classification.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="What counts as 'foundational' vs 'adjustment'">
      <rules>
        <rule>Reverses a DR's chosen alternative → foundational</rule>
        <rule>Reverses a Q↔R outcome on a load-bearing question (one whose answer drove other findings) → foundational</rule>
        <rule>Changes the scope statement in a way that invalidates prior research turns → foundational</rule>
        <rule>Adds a new artifact to the chain (ADR/UX spec) without contradicting prior decisions → adjustment</rule>
        <rule>Restates a risk area more precisely → adjustment</rule>
        <rule>Reorders the artifact chain without removing or contradicting elements → adjustment</rule>
        <rule>Adds a new edge case to the risk list → adjustment</rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

    <section title="Strike counter does not penalize honest discovery">
      <description>
        Reversals are NORMAL during D-phase — that's WHY D-phase is a
        firm checkpoint. The strike counter exists to catch
        ACCUMULATING incoherence (three reversals in one session signal
        the original Q↔R was wrong), not to discourage one honest
        course correction. Strike 1 is supposed to fire; strike 2 is
        a warning; strike 3 is the trigger.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="The override option is intentional">
      <description>
        Per Lock 31: "User can always insist on continuing past Strike 3."
        Some users have external time constraints or know context the
        agent does not (e.g., this is a throwaway exploration anyway).
        The override exists to honor that. But the bundle is then flagged
        as having been force-continued past abort threshold; ticket-verify
        will surface this for review.
      </description>
    </section>

  </guidance>

</step-file>
