<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="ticket-design" step="5" title="Finalize and Handoff">

  <step n="5" title="Finalize and Handoff">

    <goal>
      Write the locked Design Summary into the ticket body, stamp
      last_updated, re-validate the bundle, and present the handoff
      to ticket-structure.
    </goal>

    <substep n="5a" title="Write Design Summary to Worklog">
      <action>
        Append {{session.design_summary_final}} to the worklog file.
        Use the Edit tool. The section's heading is "## Design Summary"
        (level 2; the worklog uses level-2 headings for each phase-gate
        summary like Readiness Summary, Design Summary, etc.).

        Placement: after the Q↔R Readiness Summary section in the worklog
        (which ticket-grill wrote in its step 6e). The worklog journal reads:

        - Orient Summary (written by ticket-orient)
        - Q↔R Readiness Summary (written by ticket-grill)
        - Design Summary (written here)
        - (later: Structure Outline, Writing Plan, Verify Session —
          written by downstream skills)
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="5b" title="Update Frontmatter If Children Changed">
      <action>
        If any new DRs were spawned during D-phase (rare; usually DR
        creation happens in ticket-grill, but possible if a foundational
        reversal cascaded into a new DR), update the ticket's
        frontmatter `children:` array to include the new DR's alias.

        If D-phase did not spawn new DRs, this substep is a no-op.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="5c" title="Stamp last_updated">
      <action type="script">uv run {base_dir}/scripts/stamp-frontmatter.py --file "{{session.worklog_path}}" --note "D-phase complete; Design Summary written; ready for ticket-structure. Strikes: {{session.foundational_strikes}}/3."</action>
      <note>
        Per Lock 27, stamp-frontmatter.py REPLACES last_updated_note.
        The strike count is captured in the note for audit trail —
        ticket-verify will read this and surface if strikes > 0.
      </note>
    </substep>

    <substep n="5d" title="Re-Validate Bundle">
      <action type="script">thoughts validate {{session.ticket_path}} {{session.research_path}} {{session.questions_path}} {{session.worklog_path}}</action>
      <check if="validation fails">
        <action>
          Halt. Surface validation errors. Do NOT auto-fix; investigate
          which write step in this skill produced malformed output.
        </action>
      </check>
    </substep>

    <substep n="5e" title="Present Final Handoff">
      <template-output section="D-Phase Complete" critical="true">
        Design phase complete. Bundle ready for Structure.

        **Bundle location**: {{session.bundle_dir}}

        **Design Summary** (now in ticket body):

        {{session.design_summary_final}}

        **Strike counter status**: {{session.foundational_strikes}}/3
        {{if strikes > 0:}}
        ⚠️ This session had {{session.foundational_strikes}} foundational
        reversal(s). The questions file logs each strike. ticket-verify
        will surface these for review during the Verify phase.

        **Next action**: invoke `ticket-structure` from the ticketsmith
        menu (cmd: TS) to define the ticket's section/Parts shape and
        the tag-driven content recipe. ticket-structure will load this
        bundle, read the Design Summary, and propose the ticket's
        internal structure.

        If a scope or design concern surfaces during ticket-structure,
        that skill can loop back here (ticket-design) — bring fresh
        eyes; the strike counter resets per ticket-design invocation.
      </template-output>
    </substep>

  </step>

  <guidance>

    <section title="The Design Summary is a contract">
      <description>
        Once written into the ticket body, the Design Summary becomes the
        contract for the downstream phases. ticket-structure refers to
        the artifact chain to choose ticket sections. ticket-plan refers
        to the decision points to schedule subagent batches.
        ticket-write expands risk areas into concrete acceptance
        criteria. ticket-verify checks that the final ticket honors the
        Design Summary's promises.

        Drift from the Design Summary in downstream phases is a verify
        finding (severity: High typically, Critical if the drift
        invalidates a locked DR).
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Strike count visibility">
      <description>
        The strike count is captured in last_updated_note (per Lock 27,
        which replaces on each stamp). ticket-verify reads the latest
        last_updated_note and surfaces if strikes > 0. This is the
        durable audit trail; the strike_log session variable itself
        does NOT persist to disk (per the earlier-locked design
        decision that strikes live in session state only).
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Bundle status remains 'draft'">
      <description>
        D-phase does NOT transition the ticket to 'ready'. That
        transition happens at the end of ticket-verify's final step,
        gated by the user. ticket-design leaves status=draft.
      </description>
    </section>

  </guidance>

</step-file>
