<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="ticket-orient" step="4" title="Parse Request and Detect Tag">

  <step n="4" title="Parse Request and Detect Tag">

    <goal>
      Read the user's request that opened the session. Distill it into a
      one-paragraph restatement and select a CANDIDATE primary tag. The
      tag is a starting hypothesis — step 5's checkpoint may correct it,
      and ticket-grill may further refine it once the request's true nature
      surfaces during Q↔R.
    </goal>

    <substep n="4a" title="Restate the Request">
      <action>
        Distill the user's request into one or two sentences. The restatement
        should:
        - Use the canonical terms from CONTEXT.md when applicable
        - Be neutral about scope (do not infer features the user did not state)
        - Surface ambiguity explicitly ("X may mean A or B; this needs grilling")

        Store as {{session.request_restatement}}.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="4b" title="Select Candidate Primary Tag">
      <action>
        Pick ONE primary tag from the six-tag taxonomy (spec §8). Use these
        heuristics:

        - feature -> new product capability. User wants to add or change observable behavior.
        - bug -> broken behavior. User reports something works incorrectly.
        - exploration -> spike / learning goal. User wants to investigate or evaluate.
        - hotfix -> emergency fix. User signals urgency and incident context.
        - infrastructure -> setup/config/tooling. Not user-facing behavior; cross-cutting plumbing.
        - chore -> task scope. Small, well-defined task with no decisions.

        Tag selection is a CANDIDATE only. The scope checkpoint in step 5 lets
        the user redirect. Tag may further evolve during ticket-grill if
        research surfaces the request's true nature is different (e.g., a
        "feature" request that's really an exploration because foundational
        questions are unresolved).

        Store as {{session.candidate_tag}}.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="4c" title="Slug the Request">
      <action>
        Generate a kebab-case slug from the request restatement. Conventions:
        - Lowercase
        - Words separated by hyphens
        - 2-5 words maximum
        - No filler words (the, a, of) unless they clarify
        - No tag prefix (the alias-form `ticket-YYYY-MM-DD-{slug}` is added by scaffold-bundle.py)

        Examples:
        - "Add team workspaces with shared task lists" -> team-workspaces
        - "Fix invoice truncation at 1024 chars" -> invoice-truncation
        - "Investigate adopting tRPC for the API layer" -> trpc-adoption-spike

        Store as {{session.slug}}.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="4d" title="Display Tag Candidate">
      <output>
        Request parsing:
        - Restatement: {{session.request_restatement}}
        - Candidate primary tag: {{session.candidate_tag}}
        - Slug: {{session.slug}}

        Proceeding to scope checkpoint.
      </output>
    </substep>

  </step>

  <guidance>

    <section title="Why only one primary tag">
      <description>
        Primary tag selects the depth recipe in subsequent phases. Tags like
        `feature` mandate full Q↔R/D/S/P depth; `chore` minimizes ceremony.
        Mixing primary tags conflates depth signals.

        Secondary tags (security, performance, refactor, etc.) are free-form
        metadata for filtering — they do NOT change the recipe. Those are
        set during ticket-grill or ticket-write, not here.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Tag selection heuristics">
      <rules>
        <rule>If the user says "broken", "regression", "fails", "wrong" -> bug</rule>
        <rule>If the user says "explore", "spike", "investigate", "evaluate", "consider" -> exploration</rule>
        <rule>If the user says "emergency", "production down", "blocking customer", "ASAP" -> hotfix</rule>
        <rule>If the user describes plumbing (CI, build, deployment, dependencies, dev tooling) without user-facing behavior -> infrastructure</rule>
        <rule>If the user describes a small mechanical task ("update the README", "rename this field everywhere") -> chore</rule>
        <rule>Otherwise default to feature; correct at scope checkpoint or during ticket-grill</rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

    <section title="Restatement quality">
      <rules>
        <rule>The restatement is what gets presented at step 5's checkpoint — it must be precise enough for the user to spot misunderstanding</rule>
        <rule>Do not silently add scope. If the user said "team workspaces", do not write "team workspaces with billing integration"</rule>
        <rule>Do not silently subtract scope. If the user said "team workspaces with billing", do not collapse to "team workspaces"</rule>
        <rule>Surface ambiguity explicitly with parenthetical flags: "(unclear whether per-team or per-user)"</rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

    <section title="Slug discipline">
      <rules>
        <rule>The slug becomes part of the bundle directory name AND part of every file's canonical alias for the lifetime of the ticket</rule>
        <rule>It is hard to change later (touches frontmatter aliases, parent links, file paths)</rule>
        <rule>If unsure, pick the noun phrase that names the WORK, not the action verb</rule>
      </rules>
      <example type="good">team-workspaces (noun phrase, names the work)</example>
      <example type="bad">add-teams (action verb, scope-narrow)</example>
    </section>

  </guidance>

</step-file>
