<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="research-precedent" step="3" title="Assess Applicability and Synthesize Register">

  <step n="3" title="Assess Applicability and Synthesize Register">

    <substep n="3a" title="Assess Each Precedent">
      <action>
        For each candidate precedent surfaced in step 2, assess transfer
        to OUR situation (grounded in what step 1c established). Record:
        - Source: file:line / thoughts/ alias / URL
        - What it is: one line on what the precedent does
        - What matches: the dimensions on which it resembles our subject
        - What differs: the dimensions on which our context diverges
        - Transfer-fit class (factual classification, not a recommendation):
          - directly-reusable — matches closely; could be lifted or
            imported with minimal change
          - adaptable — solves the same problem in a differing context;
            transferable with the identified changes
          - informative — does not transfer directly but reveals a useful
            approach, consideration, or pitfall
          - cautionary — a precedent of what NOT to do; what went wrong
            and why

        State match/differ with evidence. Do NOT say "we should adopt
        this" — whether to adopt is the orchestrator's decision; the
        class grades the evidence, it does not prescribe an action.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="3b" title="Note Scout Follow-Ups">
      <action>
        For any external precedent whose value would require reading its
        code in depth (not just its docs), note a recommended Scout
        follow-up: the repo and what to study. This is a recommendation
        embedded in the deliverable, not a dispatch — PR hunts, Scout
        External Codebase clones.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="3c" title="Compose the Register">
      <action>
        Compose the register per references/research/document-format
        body-skeleton. Fixed top (what we sought precedent for, Summary)
        and bottom (Open Questions); the variable middle is the precedent
        entries grouped by transfer-fit class (directly-reusable first,
        then adaptable, informative, cautionary), followed by a
        Recommended Scout Follow-Ups subsection.

        When no precedent was found in any source, the register says so
        plainly and cites the negative evidence ("codebase-pattern-finder:
        no similar implementation; thoughts-locator: no prior artifact;
        web: no documented pattern") — the greenfield finding.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="3d" title="Review the Register" optional="true">
      <check if="INTERACTIVE">
        <template-output section="Precedent Register">
          Present the register for review before persistence.

          [a] Revise (re-hunt a source, sharpen an assessment)
          [c] Continue to persistence
          [y] YOLO
        </template-output>
      </check>
    </substep>

  </step>

</step-file>
