<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="ticket-grill" step="1" title="Load Bundle">

  <step n="1" title="Load Bundle">

    <goal>
      Read the entire bundle into working memory before any grilling begins.
      This step runs ONCE per session — subsequent steps may loop, but the
      bundle load is a one-time orientation activity.
    </goal>

    <substep n="1a" title="Locate the Bundle">
      <ask>
        Which ticket bundle should I grill?

        If you just completed ticket-orient, paste the bundle directory path
        it produced (under {shared_folder}/tickets/{slug}/).

        If you are resuming an existing draft, provide the bundle directory
        path or the ticket file path.
      </ask>
      <action>
        Validate the path:
        - Directory exists
        - Contains a ticket file (ticket-YYYY-MM-DD-{slug}.md)
        - Contains a research file (research-YYYY-MM-DD-{slug}.md)
        - Contains a questions file (questions-YYYY-MM-DD-{slug}.md)
        - Contains a worklog file (worklog-YYYY-MM-DD-{slug}.md)
        - All files parse with valid YAML frontmatter

        Store the bundle paths in session:
        - {{session.ticket_path}}
        - {{session.research_path}}
        - {{session.questions_path}}
        - {{session.worklog_path}}
        - {{session.bundle_dir}}

        If any file is missing or malformed, halt and report — the user must
        re-run ticket-orient or fix the bundle.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="1b" title="Read Bundle Files">
      <action>
        Read ALL three files completely. No skimming, no offset/limit.
        Extract from the ticket file:
        - Frontmatter: kind, status, aliases, tags (primary tag is tags[0]),
          owner, researcher, date, last_updated, parent, children, depends_on
        - Body: user-request restatement (written by ticket-orient)

        Extract from the research file:
        - Frontmatter: parent ticket alias
        - Body: any prior research findings (empty on a fresh bundle)

        Extract from the questions file:
        - Frontmatter: parent ticket alias
        - Body: any prior Q↔R entries (empty on a fresh bundle)

        Extract from the worklog file:
        - Body: the Orient Summary + Open Threads (written by ticket-orient at handoff)

        Store in session:
        - {{session.primary_tag}}
        - {{session.slug}}
        - {{session.shared_folder}} (derived from the bundle path)
        - {{session.orient_summary}} (the full Orient Summary block)
        - {{session.prior_questions}} (list of resolved questions from prior turns, if resuming)
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="1c" title="Read CONTEXT.md (if exists)">
      <action>
        Re-read CONTEXT.md or CONTEXT-MAP.md to refresh the glossary in working
        memory. ticket-orient already read it once, but a resumption session
        may have lost that state, and the glossary may have evolved between
        sessions.

        If neither exists, set {{session.glossary}} = "none" — lazy-create
        will trigger on the first resolved term during this skill.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="1d" title="Read Linked Decision Records (if any)">
      <action>
        If the ticket frontmatter `children:` array references any
        `decision-YYYY-MM-DD-*` aliases, resolve and read each one. These
        are decisions already locked in prior turns. They constrain what
        ticket-grill is allowed to revisit — a DR's decision is immutable.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="1e" title="Display Bundle Summary">
      <output>
        Bundle loaded:
        - Slug: {{session.slug}}
        - Primary tag: {{session.primary_tag}}
        - Status: {{session.ticket_status}}
        - Owner: {{session.owner}}
        - Glossary: {{session.glossary_summary}}
        - Prior Q&A entries: {{count}}
        - Linked DRs: {{count}} ({{aliases_if_any}})

        Orient Summary present: yes

        Entering Q↔R loop. First turn begins with current-state orientation.
      </output>
    </substep>

  </step>

  <guidance>

    <section title="Single-load discipline">
      <description>
        This step runs ONCE. Subsequent steps may loop (step 2 -> step 6 ->
        loop back to step 2), but the bundle is read once into session
        state. Re-reading on every loop iteration wastes context and risks
        drift (a step 5 edit changes the file; re-reading it in step 2 of
        the next iteration would mix turn-N writes with turn-(N+1) reads).
        Instead, the agent maintains session state and edits files
        purposefully in step 5.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Resumption is normal">
      <description>
        ticket-grill is designed to resume cleanly. A session may have run
        through three turns previously, hit context pressure, compacted,
        and now restart at step 1 of ticket-grill with the same bundle
        path. The Orient Summary + prior Q&A entries + research findings on
        disk are sufficient to pick up exactly where the previous session
        left off — no separate handoff document is required.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Failure modes at load">
      <rules>
        <rule>Missing bundle file -> halt and direct user to re-run ticket-orient or fix the bundle</rule>
        <rule>Malformed frontmatter -> halt and surface the validation error</rule>
        <rule>Frontmatter status not in {draft, ready, active} -> halt; the bundle is not in a grillable state</rule>
        <rule>No Orient Summary section in the questions file AND no prior Q&A -> warn; the user may have skipped ticket-orient. Offer to proceed anyway (degraded — first turn must re-do orient work in-skill) or to abort and run ticket-orient first</rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

  </guidance>

</step-file>
