<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="ticket-grill" step="2" title="Orient on Current State">

  <step n="2" title="Orient on Current State">

    <goal>
      Before formulating new questions, take stock of what is currently known
      and what is unknown. Identify the highest-value gap to close THIS turn.
      This step is the loop's re-entry point — every turn restarts here.
    </goal>

    <substep n="2a" title="Inventory the Known">
      <action>
        List what is currently established, from the bundle and any
        accumulated session findings:
        - Scope facts (restatement, primary tag, slug)
        - Glossary terms resolved in CONTEXT.md
        - Research findings recorded in the research file
        - Decisions locked in linked DRs
        - Edge cases identified in prior turns
        - User stances from prior Q&A entries

        Be terse. One line per fact. The point is to identify what does NOT
        need re-litigating, not to recite a transcript.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="2b" title="Inventory the Unknown">
      <action>
        Enumerate the gaps. Categories:
        - Scoping gaps (what the work is supposed to cover; what it is NOT)
        - Codebase facts (how the system currently behaves; what exists)
        - Domain facts (how similar systems handle similar problems)
        - Decision points (alternatives with real trade-offs that need a chosen path)
        - Edge cases (deletion behavior, error states, permissions, concurrency)
        - Constraints (deadlines, regulatory, compatibility)
        - Term ambiguity (words used by the user that need glossary precision)

        Be honest. If a gap is "we have not even thought about X yet", surface
        it. Suppressed unknowns become surprises during ticket-design or
        implementation.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="2c" title="Pick the Highest-Value Gap">
      <action>
        Select ONE gap to close this turn. Heuristics:
        - Closest to scope > deeper detail (scope first)
        - Blocks other gaps > stands alone (unblockers first)
        - Single-question shape > multi-pronged (cheaper first, unless a multi-prong is genuinely required)
        - User-answerable now > research-bound (don't burn subagent calls when the user can answer immediately)

        Store as {{session.turn_focus}}: a one-sentence description of the
        gap being closed this turn.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="2d" title="Declare Mode for This Turn">
      <action>
        Q↔R has four sub-activities (QRDSPIV §Q↔R). Declare which the
        current turn will primarily use:

        - **Brainstorming**: vague idea -> concrete possibilities. Use when the user's request is fuzzy and needs shape before research can target it.
        - **Research**: factual gathering. Use when the gap is "what exists" or "what do others do".
        - **Elicitation**: targeted question to the user. Use when only the user can answer (preferences, scoping decisions, business constraints).
        - **Prototyping**: throwaway runnable artifact (LOGIC or UI). Use when the gap is "I do not know if this is feasible" or "I do not know what this would feel like".

        Most turns will use one mode dominantly; some may blend two. Store
        as {{session.turn_mode}}.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="2e" title="Display Turn Plan">
      <output>
        Turn {{turn_number}} plan:
        - Focus: {{session.turn_focus}}
        - Mode: {{session.turn_mode}}
        - Known facts brought forward: {{count}}
        - Unknowns enumerated: {{count}}

        Proceeding to question formulation.
      </output>
    </substep>

  </step>

  <guidance>

    <section title="One gap per turn">
      <description>
        Multi-gap turns blur subagent dispatch and dilute the user's
        attention at the per-turn checkpoint. One focused gap per turn
        makes the Q&A log readable and the readiness gate evaluable.
        If two gaps are genuinely entangled (cannot answer one without the
        other), pick the more upstream one and let the second emerge from
        its resolution.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Hide-the-intent does NOT apply here">
      <description>
        Spec §3 and QRDSPIV note that "hide the intent" applies only to
        implementation Q↔R (where the agent gathers codebase facts WITHOUT
        reading what the spec says to change, to prevent premature
        opinion-forming). At the ticket-writing layer the agent is open
        about what is being grilled — the user is a participant in the
        grilling, not a subject of it. State the focus plainly; do not
        sandbag.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="When the bundle is already rich">
      <description>
        On later turns, the bundle has accumulated research findings,
        resolved Q&A entries, and possibly DRs. The "known" inventory in 2a
        compresses these into a one-line-per-fact summary. The point is
        not to re-prove what is already on disk; the point is to choose
        what to investigate NEXT.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="If the unknown inventory is empty">
      <description>
        If 2b produces no genuine unknowns AND step 6's readiness criteria
        are all clearly met, the loop is converging. In that case the next
        turn IS the readiness gate — skip 2c/2d and proceed straight to
        step 6 to confirm and exit. But: do not force this early. The most
        common failure mode is exiting Q↔R too soon, not too late.
      </description>
    </section>

  </guidance>

</step-file>
