<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<step-file skill="ticket-grill" step="6" title="Readiness Gate">

  <step n="6" title="Readiness Gate">

    <goal>
      Evaluate whether the Q↔R loop has produced enough understanding to
      exit to the Design phase. If all five readiness criteria from QRDSPIV
      are met, summarize and hand off to ticket-design. If any is not met,
      loop back to step 2 for another turn.
    </goal>

    <substep n="6a" title="Evaluate the Five Criteria">
      <action>
        Check each criterion against the accumulated bundle state. Per
        QRDSPIV §Q↔R Readiness Criteria and spec §3.1:

        1. **The problem is clearly scoped (user confirmed)**
           - Restatement in the ticket body matches what was grilled
           - Scope boundaries are explicit (in-scope AND out-of-scope clear)
           - User has confirmed scope, not just acknowledged it

        2. **The current state is factually mapped (codebase, artifacts)**
           - Research file has factual findings for every relevant code area
           - No "we don't know if X exists" gaps remain on critical questions
           - Subagent findings have been synthesized, not just collected

        3. **Impact is understood (what artifacts need creating/modifying)**
           - The downstream artifacts implied by this ticket are identified
             at a high level (e.g., "this needs an ADR for the data isolation
             pattern; a spec for team APIs; an implementation across N
             vertical slices")
           - Risk areas are surfaced (e.g., "auth middleware refactor will
             touch 47 test files")

        4. **Edge cases are identified (deletion, error states, permissions)**
           - Edge cases relevant to the primary tag are enumerated and have
             chosen answers
           - "What happens when X is deleted?" / "What happens on permission
             denial?" / "What's the concurrency story?" — at least asked,
             ideally answered

        5. **The agent can articulate what it knows WITHOUT being asked**
           - Most rigorous criterion. The agent should be able to walk
             through the scope, current state, design implications, risks,
             and edge cases from the bundle alone, without re-reading the
             user's original message.

        For each criterion, record:
        - PASS / NOT YET
        - One-line evidence (e.g., "ticket body lines 12-25 cover scope;
          out-of-scope listed in lines 30-35")

        Store as {{session.readiness_check}}.
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="6b" title="Decide Loop or Exit">
      <check if="all five criteria pass">
        <action>
          The loop is ready to exit. Proceed to substep 6c.
        </action>
      </check>
      <check if="one or more criteria fail">
        <action>
          The loop continues. Proceed to substep 6d to surface the gap and
          loop back to step 2.
        </action>
      </check>
    </substep>

    <substep n="6c" title="Confirm Exit With User">
      <ask>
        Present the user with the readiness summary:

        Readiness check ({{turn_count}} turns elapsed):
        1. Problem scoped: PASS — {{evidence}}
        2. Current state mapped: PASS — {{evidence}}
        3. Impact understood: PASS — {{evidence}}
        4. Edge cases identified: PASS — {{evidence}}
        5. Agent can articulate unprompted: PASS — {{summary of articulation}}

        Bundle artifacts:
        - Ticket: {{session.ticket_path}} ({{ticket_body_line_count}} lines)
        - Research: {{session.research_path}} ({{turn_count}} turn entries)
        - Questions: {{session.questions_path}} ({{question_count}} Q&A entries)
        - Decision Records: {{count and aliases}}
        - CONTEXT.md updates: {{terms added this session}}

        Ready to transition to Design phase (ticket-design)?
        - Confirm (Recommended): exit Q↔R; recommend ticket-design via menu
        - One more turn: I see a gap — describe it
        - Pause: stop here; bundle is on disk for later resumption
      </ask>
      <check if="user confirms">
        <action>
          Proceed to substep 6e (final handoff write).
        </action>
      </check>
      <check if="user requests one more turn">
        <action>
          Capture the gap into session state as the next turn's focus.
          Loop back to step 2.
        </action>
        <goto step="2"/>
      </check>
      <check if="user pauses">
        <action>
          The bundle on disk is the handoff state. Acknowledge and exit
          the skill without writing a handoff section to the questions
          file beyond what step 5 already wrote. The user can resume by
          re-invoking ticket-grill on the same bundle path.
        </action>
      </check>
    </substep>

    <substep n="6d" title="Surface the Gap and Loop">
      <ask>
        Readiness not yet met:
        {{for each failing criterion:}}
        - {{criterion N}}: NOT YET — {{what's missing}}

        I propose the next turn focus on: {{agent's recommended next gap}}.

        - Accept (Recommended): proceed with the proposed focus
        - Redirect: focus on a different gap; describe
        - Force-exit: skip readiness and exit anyway (NOT RECOMMENDED — this
          will produce an under-grilled ticket that will surface gaps in
          ticket-design or ticket-verify)
        - Pause: stop here; bundle is on disk for later resumption
      </ask>
      <check if="user accepts or redirects">
        <action>
          Capture the next turn's focus into session state. Loop back to step 2.
        </action>
        <goto step="2"/>
      </check>
      <check if="user force-exits">
        <action>
          Note the force-exit in the questions file (which criteria were
          unmet at exit). The bundle is technically usable but flagged
          as under-grilled. Proceed to substep 6e.
        </action>
      </check>
      <check if="user pauses">
        <action>
          Exit the skill. Bundle on disk is the handoff state.
        </action>
      </check>
    </substep>

    <substep n="6e" title="Write Readiness Summary to Worklog">
      <action>
        Append a Readiness Summary section to the WORKLOG file (the QRDSPIV
        journal — not the ticket, which holds only the deliverable). Format:

        ## Q↔R Readiness Summary

        - Turns elapsed: {{turn_count}}
        - Status: READY (or FORCE-EXIT with caveats)

        **Scope**: {{one-paragraph restatement, refined by grilling}}
        **Current state**: {{one-paragraph synthesis of research findings}}
        **Impact**: {{one-paragraph downstream artifact map}}
        **Risk areas**: {{bullet list}}
        **Edge cases addressed**: {{bullet list}}
        **Decision Records spawned**: {{list of DR aliases}}

        Use the Edit tool on the worklog file. Then stamp last_updated:

        uv run {base_dir}/scripts/stamp-frontmatter.py --file "{{session.worklog_path}}" --note "Q↔R complete; readiness gate passed; ready for ticket-design."
      </action>
    </substep>

    <substep n="6f" title="Present Final Handoff">
      <template-output section="Q↔R Complete" critical="true">
        Grilling complete. Bundle ready for Design.

        **Bundle location**: {{session.bundle_dir}}

        **Turns elapsed**: {{turn_count}}
        **DRs spawned**: {{count}}
        **CONTEXT.md updates**: {{terms_count}}

        **Readiness Summary** has been written into the ticket body (see
        the ticket file).

        **Next action**: invoke the `ticket-design` skill from the
        ticketsmith menu (cmd: TD) for the Design phase. ticket-design will
        load this bundle, read the Readiness Summary, and run the
        brain-surgery alignment conversation on the work to be done.

        If you need to resume the Q↔R loop later (e.g., ticket-design
        surfaces a scoping gap and loops back), re-invoke ticket-grill on
        the same bundle path — it will pick up from the readiness state
        and run an additional turn.
      </template-output>
    </substep>

  </step>

  <guidance>

    <section title="The fifth criterion is the strict one">
      <description>
        Criteria 1-4 are objective checks against the bundle's content.
        Criterion 5 — "the agent can articulate what it knows WITHOUT being
        asked" — is the rigorous one. If the agent can only articulate the
        work by re-reading the user's original request or by paraphrasing
        prior Q&A, the loop is not actually done. The articulation should
        flow from the bundle's accumulated state.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Force-exit is a defined failure mode">
      <rules>
        <rule>Force-exit produces an under-grilled ticket. ticket-design or ticket-verify will surface the gaps later, but at higher cost</rule>
        <rule>Force-exit should be RARE — reserved for cases where the user has external time pressure</rule>
        <rule>The questions file MUST record which criteria were unmet at force-exit; ticket-verify will check this</rule>
        <rule>Do not encourage force-exit; offer it as an explicit option but recommend against it</rule>
      </rules>
    </section>

    <section title="Loop-back is normal">
      <description>
        Spec §3.2 lists backward loops as permitted. ticket-design may
        return to ticket-grill if D-phase alignment reveals a scoping gap.
        That re-entry is handled by step 1 (load bundle) detecting prior
        Q&A entries and resuming from the readiness gate's last failure
        state. No special "resume mode" is needed.
      </description>
    </section>

    <section title="Three-strike escalation is a separate concern">
      <description>
        Per Lock 31, when the user reverses a foundational decision after
        D-phase alignment, a three-strike pattern escalates to abort
        recommendation. That pattern is OWNED BY ticket-design (the
        D-phase skill), not here — ticket-grill simply absorbs the new
        focus and loops. The strike counter sits in ticket-design's
        session state.
      </description>
    </section>

  </guidance>

</step-file>
